<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Innervoce Blogs</title>
    <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Innervoce Blogs</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 18:18:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals for the first half of 2018</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2018/01/07/goals-for-the-first-half-of-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 18:18:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2018/01/07/goals-for-the-first-half-of-2018/</guid>
      
        <description>

&lt;p&gt;A very happy new year to the readers of my blogs. It is time for the semi-annual update about my blogging and learning goals. And I must say there are some interesting goals that I conjuring up for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;status-of-2017-second-half-goals&#34;&gt;Status of 2017 second half goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had set a goal to write 3 blogs in the second half of 2017 without specifically talking about what those blogs were. The reason was that I was experimenting with technologies like Docker and Cassandra. So I could plan specific topics related to these upfront.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Score: &lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; In the end, I wrote two blogs about Docker. For 2 out of a goal 3 should fetch me better score, I really feel I could have written one more blog. I was split between going further deeper in Docker related to technologies or skim the surface of several other technologies. Eventually I have decided to go breadth-first for reasons best known to me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals-for-first-half-of-2018&#34;&gt;Goals for first half of 2018&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first half of 2018 I plan to write couple of blogs &lt;strong&gt;at most.&lt;/strong&gt; This will allow me to spend time on cleaning up my existing blogs &lt;strong&gt;&amp;#8211; a long overdue task&lt;/strong&gt;. Since I need to spend more time on a critical activity, I have not planned for specific topics as yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main goal can be summarized as &lt;strong&gt;Blog rationalization&lt;/strong&gt;. And I will describe what I am planning to do. Currently I have two blogs one active and the other dead for all practical purposes. These blogs are hosted through a paid account at a Web Hosting provider but I also use Google services to host my mail for the same domains. The goal is to consolidate and also explore newer options to host my blogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;blog-rationalization-plan&#34;&gt;Blog Rationalization Plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.srirams.org/&#34;&gt;personal blog at www.srirams.org&lt;/a&gt; is in a moribund state. I have hardly blogged at a personal level and I strongly feel that Facebook is a better medium for personal posts.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will be shutting this blog down very soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.innervoice.in/blogs/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;technical blog&lt;/em&gt; at www.innervoice.in/blogs&lt;/a&gt; is quite active. In fact some of the blogs appear at the top in Google search. The interesting aspect about this domain is that the blogs are hosted on a Hosting provider platform but my mails are managed using Google Suite (GSuite) for Business. The GSuite includes applications like Google Sites that can be used for blogging. Though not a ideal replacement for WordPress blog platform (that I use today), GSuite meets most of my needs as a solo and relatively infrequent blogger. Another alternative to using GSuite is to use a _paid account_ at WordPress.com.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To reduce account management overheads (security, SW updates, passwords) I want to migrate to GSuite Sites or WordPress.com based blogs. I already have GSuite paid account so WordPress.com will incur additional cost.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Migration to GSuite will require considerable work since I need to migrate all the existing links. It will be a time consuming process and something I am determined to do. I also need to be careful about the &lt;em&gt;loss of functionality&lt;/em&gt; in this migration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have paid my Web Hosting provider for 1 more year &amp;#8211; so I do have some time but the migration of blogs, their URLs without impacting search ranking needs to be carefully done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overall the goal is clear &amp;#8211; get away from my Web Hosting provider. And this requires regular weekend work, reading and execution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The final aspect of the &lt;em&gt;Blog rationalization&lt;/em&gt; is to &lt;strong&gt;start blogging on LinkedIn&lt;/strong&gt;. I have been blogging about technical topics whereas my work experience is more on the managerial side. Moreover writing about non-technical yet professional topics will challenge my writing skills more. I will be posting about this on my LinkedIn account soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8211; as you can see I am trying to consolidate the various online blogging platforms and align them to meet my future plans. &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can really help me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by sharing ideas and suggestions about Medium, other online blogging platforms etc. Or sharing tools that will help me with the rationalization.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>