<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Opinion on Sriram S - Innervoice</title>
    <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/categories/opinion/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Opinion on Sriram S - Innervoice</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 18:05:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/categories/opinion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux Network Namespace – WILT</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/12/17/linux-network-namespace-wilt/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 18:05:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/12/17/linux-network-namespace-wilt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the next installment of &amp;ldquo;What I learnt today&amp;rdquo; or WILT, I briefly touch upon Network Namespace. I came across Namespace as part of my ongoing study of OpenStack networking. Namespaces are powerful constructs in Linux that allows you to create a &lt;strong&gt;copy of the TCP/IP network stack &amp;#8211; all the way from the Ethernet interfaces (L2), routing tables etc.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals for the first half of 2014</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/02/16/goals-first-half-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 16:15:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/02/16/goals-first-half-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like previous years, I want to continue the habit of sharing my goals around blogging and learning experiments. Clearly, this update for the first half of 2014 is already late. In addition, I did slip up on the important goals of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review – 101 Myths and Realities @ The Office</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/01/07/book-review-101-myths-realities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2013 03:00:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/01/07/book-review-101-myths-realities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most management, leadership and self-help books tend to give generic advice and suggestions about how to manage your career at workplace. But in life we find that even similar situations require different actions. The main reason for this is that each situation involves different perspectives, people and possibilities. The book, &lt;strong&gt;101 Myths and Reality @ the Office&lt;/strong&gt; provides a situational view of our work environment. The book deals with practical situations such as appraisals, hike, promotions etc. And for each situation it gives relevant suggestions to employees as well as managers. &lt;strong&gt;This will be a great addition to your office bookshelf as an anytime reference&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>