<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cloud Computing on Sriram S - Innervoice</title>
    <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/categories/cloud-computing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cloud Computing on Sriram S - Innervoice</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 02:39:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/categories/cloud-computing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Ocata release install scripts for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/06/03/ocata-openstack-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 02:39:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/06/03/ocata-openstack-install/</guid>
      <description>Ocata is the most recent release of OpenStack. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the Ocata is the most recent release of OpenStack. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the server as per the installation guide. This is a collection of scripts that should help you get going with OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s latest release. I have been developing these scripts to help me with my blogging and personal learning projects</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newton release install scripts for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/05/02/openstack-newton-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 05:07:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/05/02/openstack-newton-install/</guid>
      <description>Newton is one the recent releases of OpenStack. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the Newton release of OpenStack on Ubuntu 16.04 as per the installation guide. As part of my blogging, book writing projects, I have the need to install OpenStack many times. And I have been automating the installation by writing simple shell scripts. The result is a collection of scripts that should help you get going with OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s latest release.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Horizon: extending the dashboard – Part 2</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/01/22/openstack-horizon-extending-dashboard-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 17:42:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/01/22/openstack-horizon-extending-dashboard-part-2/</guid>
      <description>In this second installment of my blog on OpenStack Horizon, I will take you through different source code files that make a custom OpenStack dashboard. As a recap from the first installment, I will show you how to create a custom dashboard to view all the Neutron &amp;ldquo;ports&amp;rdquo; in your OpenStack based cloud.
Enabling OpenStack Horizon Dashboard Django framework loads and enables dashboards based on entries present in the enabled directory of OpenStack Dashboard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Horizon: extending the dashboard – Part 1</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/12/27/openstack-horizon-customizing-the-dashboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 10:31:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/12/27/openstack-horizon-customizing-the-dashboard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OpenStack Horizon is the project that provides the web based dashboard for OpenStack based clouds. In this 2-part blog I will show you how you can extend the dashboard. Customizing and extending is one of the most powerful capabilities in OpenStack and in private cloud environments it is common to add additional enhancements to address an organization&amp;rsquo;s needs.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Announcement and Launch discounts</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/10/26/book-announcement-launch-discounts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 14:57:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/10/26/book-announcement-launch-discounts/</guid>
      <description>My second book titled &amp;ldquo;Software Defined Networking with OpenStack&amp;rdquo; is almost ready to be available publicly. You can find the overview of the book below.
With OpenStack Summit going on in Barcelona, my publishers, Packt, have graciously announced pre-launch discounts for the new book. You can get the following discounts:
 15% off on Print copies (code: SDNWOS15) 50% off on eBooks (code: SDNWOS50)  Both discounts available at my publisher website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mitaka on Ubuntu – install scripts for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/07/06/mitaka-on-ubuntu-install-scripts-for-openstack/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 06:45:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/07/06/mitaka-on-ubuntu-install-scripts-for-openstack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mitaka is the most recent release of OpenStack and currently it is supports &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.openstack.org/mitaka/install-guide-ubuntu/&#34;&gt;Ubuntu 14.04 LTS (trusty)&lt;/a&gt;. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the Mitaka release of OpenStack on Ubuntu. As part of my blogging, book writing projects, I have had the need to install OpenStack many times. And I have been automating the installation by writing simple shell scripts. The result is a collection of scripts that should help you get going with OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s latest release.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Controller Logs – view using a browser</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/06/27/openstack-controller-logs-view-using-browser/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2016 18:22:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/06/27/openstack-controller-logs-view-using-browser/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OpenStack is made up of various services. These services have their own logs stored under /var/log directory. While working on OpenStack related projects it is quite common to monitor the logs for any problems or errors. While the tail command is the most popular, there are many benefits of using web browser to view the logs. In this blog let us see how we can view OpenStack Controller Logs using a browser.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PyCharm and OpenStack programming</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/01/02/pycharm-and-openstack-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 17:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/01/02/pycharm-and-openstack-programming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OpenStack is based on the Python programming language and DevStack is the most common development and test environment for OpenStack. If you are doing serious, professional programming around OpenStack, it is very useful to have a proper development environment. In this blog, I will show you how to use the &lt;strong&gt;PyCharm IDE&lt;/strong&gt; from Jetbrains for your OpenStack programming. I will use the &lt;strong&gt;Neutron ML2 driver code from my book &lt;a href=&#34;http://goo.gl/TeXSYQ&#34;&gt;OpenStack Networking Cookbook&lt;/a&gt; to guide you&lt;/strong&gt; in setting up the PyCharm IDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing: OpenStack Networking Cookbook</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/10/23/openstack-networking-cookbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2015 16:47:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/10/23/openstack-networking-cookbook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My first publication &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/1NrKjty&#34;&gt;OpenStack Networking Cookbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is now available for purchase. It is available as a printed book as well as e-book. OpenStack is a rapidly evolving cloud platform and Networking (Neutron) is one of its critical components. The current trends of SDN and NFV make OpenStack Networking even more exciting and complex. I have co-authored the book with a colleague and the overall experience of writing a book was very satisfying.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ports in OpenStack Neutron</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/07/04/ports-in-openstack-neutron/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2015 18:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/07/04/ports-in-openstack-neutron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OpenStack supports rich abstractions to handle &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/&#34;&gt;virtual networking needs in a cloud&lt;/a&gt;. As a user the most visible entities are the Network, Subnets, Routers, Firewall etc. But if we consider ingress and egress points for data traffic, the most critical entity is the Port. OpenStack Neutron Ports are usually created automatically as part of other user operations. However the CLI allows users to create Ports independently as well.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VirtualBox networking settings for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/06/14/virtualbox-networking-settings-for-openstack/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2015 14:58:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/06/14/virtualbox-networking-settings-for-openstack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The best way to learn OpenStack is by installing, running and playing with it directly. In this blog, I will share the details of the VirtualBox based multi-node OpenStack installation. I will be focusing &lt;strong&gt;only on the networking aspects when using VirtualBox&lt;/strong&gt;. I will also share some tips that are important in this deployment. This blog will not cover the steps to install and create a virtual machine using VirtualBox.

While most people use DevStack to accomplish this I prefer to setup a multi-node installation. This is important for me because much of my work related to OpenStack revolves around Networking. Another reason is that a multi-node installation is what real users of OpenStack will also be deploying.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Neutron Plugins and Agents</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/03/31/openstack-neutron-plugins-and-agents/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 16:55:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/03/31/openstack-neutron-plugins-and-agents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I briefly talked about OpenStack Neutron plugins and agents in &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2015/01/13/openstack-neutron-components/&#34;&gt;my blog about OpenStack Neutron components&lt;/a&gt;. In this blog, let us go a step further and understand the roles of plugins and the agents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Neutron – the components</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/01/13/openstack-neutron-components/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 18:20:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/01/13/openstack-neutron-components/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Neutron is the networking project within the OpenStack cloud platform. The purpose of OpenStack Neutron is to provide physical and virtual network resources to the instances (or virtual machines). Before you continue to read this article I would recommend that you read about &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/&#34;&gt;OpenStack networking concepts&lt;/a&gt;. To appreciate the architecture and the functionality of Neutron, it is important to understand the components that are part of Neutron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux Network Namespace – WILT</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/12/17/linux-network-namespace-wilt/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 18:05:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/12/17/linux-network-namespace-wilt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the next installment of &amp;ldquo;What I learnt today&amp;rdquo; or WILT, I briefly touch upon Network Namespace. I came across Namespace as part of my ongoing study of OpenStack networking. Namespaces are powerful constructs in Linux that allows you to create a &lt;strong&gt;copy of the TCP/IP network stack -all the way from the Ethernet interfaces (L2), routing tables etc.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up OpenStack at home</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/11/13/setting-openstack-home/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2014 18:26:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/11/13/setting-openstack-home/</guid>
      <description>The goal of this blog is to share some details about how I have setup a cost-effective OpenStack Lab at home. For most enthusiasts, DevStack is the preferred way to experiment with OpenStack. But I wanted something more realistic for my experiments.
OpenStack is intended for multi-tenant, distributed and highly scalable cloud. To appreciate its architecture I needed to move beyond DevStack. With a more realistic setup, you can understand how the distributed OpenStack components interact with each other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Networking – an introduction</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2014 19:56:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I continue the series on virtual networking with an overview of OpenStack networking concepts. OpenStack is an open source project with an aim to create a scalable cloud operating platform. The primary goal of this software platform is to help build public and private clouds. Specifically it allows users to build and operate infrastructure as a service or &lt;strong&gt;IaaS&lt;/strong&gt; clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Virtual Networks – Ports and VLAN</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/30/understanding-virtual-networks-ports-and-vlan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2012 18:01:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/30/understanding-virtual-networks-ports-and-vlan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2012/08/16/understanding-virtual-networks-the-basics/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; we looked at the fundamental building blocks of physical and virtual networks. Now let us look at two key concepts in physical and virtual networks. They are Ports and VLAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Virtual Networks – The Basics</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/16/understanding-virtual-networks-the-basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 04:35:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/16/understanding-virtual-networks-the-basics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In order understand Virtual Networking let us start with the simplest network that many of us operate every day – our home network. The picture below captures what a typical home network looks like. I am sure most of us use wireless rather than wired networks at home but the underlying concepts are very much alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Virtual Networks</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/16/understanding-virtual-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 04:34:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/16/understanding-virtual-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Upcoming technologies like OpenFlow and SDN are altering the networking landscape very quickly. The underlying drivers are Cloud Computing and Virtualization. Servers, Storage and Networking make up the trinity for effective Cloud computing strategy. Servers and Storage Virtualization has helped drive the adoption of flexible cloud services already. Now it is time for Network Virtualization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>