<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vm on Sriram S - Innervoice</title>
    <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/tags/vm/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vm on Sriram S - Innervoice</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 16:55:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/tags/vm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Neutron Plugins and Agents</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/03/31/openstack-neutron-plugins-and-agents/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 16:55:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/03/31/openstack-neutron-plugins-and-agents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I briefly talked about OpenStack Neutron plugins and agents in &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2015/01/13/openstack-neutron-components/&#34;&gt;my blog about OpenStack Neutron components&lt;/a&gt;. In this blog, let us go a step further and understand the roles of plugins and the agents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up OpenStack at home</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/11/13/setting-openstack-home/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2014 18:26:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/11/13/setting-openstack-home/</guid>
      <description>The goal of this blog is to share some details about how I have setup a cost-effective OpenStack Lab at home. For most enthusiasts, DevStack is the preferred way to experiment with OpenStack. But I wanted something more realistic for my experiments.
OpenStack is intended for multi-tenant, distributed and highly scalable cloud. To appreciate its architecture I needed to move beyond DevStack. With a more realistic setup, you can understand how the distributed OpenStack components interact with each other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Networking – an introduction</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2014 19:56:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I continue the series on virtual networking with an overview of OpenStack networking concepts. OpenStack is an open source project with an aim to create a scalable cloud operating platform. The primary goal of this software platform is to help build public and private clouds. Specifically it allows users to build and operate infrastructure as a service or &lt;strong&gt;IaaS&lt;/strong&gt; clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KVM and QEMU – do you know the connection?</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/03/09/kvm-and-qemu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2014 18:58:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/03/09/kvm-and-qemu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you were to ask someone &amp;ldquo;what is the most popular open source hypervisor&amp;rdquo; chances are that the answer will be KVM. Indeed KVM (or Kernel-based Virtual Machine) has played a key role in the open source Linux based virtualization environment. However is it really a hypervisor? Moreover, can KVM by itself run virtual machines? We will delve more into such questions in this blog. We will also understand the relationship between KVM and QEMU (Quick EMUlator).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tap Interfaces and Linux Bridge</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/12/08/tap-interfaces-linux-bridge/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2013 06:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/12/08/tap-interfaces-linux-bridge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2013/12/02/linux-bridge-virtual-networking/&#34;&gt;previous blog of this series&lt;/a&gt; we saw that using Linux bridge we can connect a virtual Ethernet port of a VM to the physical Ethernet port of the hypervisor server. Let us now focus a bit more on these virtual ports to see what happens behind the scenes to make virtual networking actually work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux Bridge and Virtual Networking</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/12/02/linux-bridge-virtual-networking/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 18:00:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/12/02/linux-bridge-virtual-networking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Software defined networking (SDN) is the current wave sweeping the networking industry. And one of the key enablers of SDN is virtual networking. While SDN and virtual networking are in vogue these days, the support for virtual networking is not a recent development. And Linux bridge has been the pioneer in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>