<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Virtual Switch on Sriram S - Innervoice</title>
    <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/tags/virtual-switch/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Virtual Switch on Sriram S - Innervoice</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2014 19:56:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/tags/virtual-switch/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Networking – an introduction</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2014 19:56:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I continue the series on virtual networking with an overview of OpenStack networking concepts. OpenStack is an open source project with an aim to create a scalable cloud operating platform. The primary goal of this software platform is to help build public and private clouds. Specifically it allows users to build and operate infrastructure as a service or &lt;strong&gt;IaaS&lt;/strong&gt; clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to VMware Virtual Networking</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/02/16/introduction-vmware-virtual-networking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 18:15:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/02/16/introduction-vmware-virtual-networking/</guid>
      <description>In the previous blog we saw how Linux supports virtual networking using bridges. VMware vSphere is the most popular hypervisor brand in the world and it is natural that it also supports virtual networking. In fact vSphere supports some very advanced networking functions, that are not available in most of the other hypervisors.
Let me introduce the key elements of VMware virtual networking. After reading this blog, I recommend that you read the official guide about virtual networking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tap Interfaces and Linux Bridge</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/12/08/tap-interfaces-linux-bridge/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2013 06:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/12/08/tap-interfaces-linux-bridge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2013/12/02/linux-bridge-virtual-networking/&#34;&gt;previous blog of this series&lt;/a&gt; we saw that using Linux bridge we can connect a virtual Ethernet port of a VM to the physical Ethernet port of the hypervisor server. Let us now focus a bit more on these virtual ports to see what happens behind the scenes to make virtual networking actually work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux Bridge and Virtual Networking</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/12/02/linux-bridge-virtual-networking/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 18:00:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/12/02/linux-bridge-virtual-networking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Software defined networking (SDN) is the current wave sweeping the networking industry. And one of the key enablers of SDN is virtual networking. While SDN and virtual networking are in vogue these days, the support for virtual networking is not a recent development. And Linux bridge has been the pioneer in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Virtual Networks – Ports and VLAN</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/30/understanding-virtual-networks-ports-and-vlan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2012 18:01:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/30/understanding-virtual-networks-ports-and-vlan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2012/08/16/understanding-virtual-networks-the-basics/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; we looked at the fundamental building blocks of physical and virtual networks. Now let us look at two key concepts in physical and virtual networks. They are Ports and VLAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Virtual Networks – The Basics</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/16/understanding-virtual-networks-the-basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 04:35:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/16/understanding-virtual-networks-the-basics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In order understand Virtual Networking let us start with the simplest network that many of us operate every day – our home network. The picture below captures what a typical home network looks like. I am sure most of us use wireless rather than wired networks at home but the underlying concepts are very much alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Virtual Networks</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/16/understanding-virtual-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 04:34:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2012/08/16/understanding-virtual-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Upcoming technologies like OpenFlow and SDN are altering the networking landscape very quickly. The underlying drivers are Cloud Computing and Virtualization. Servers, Storage and Networking make up the trinity for effective Cloud computing strategy. Servers and Storage Virtualization has helped drive the adoption of flexible cloud services already. Now it is time for Network Virtualization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>