<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ubuntu on Sriram S - Innervoice</title>
    <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/tags/ubuntu/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ubuntu on Sriram S - Innervoice</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 05:07:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/tags/ubuntu/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Newton release install scripts for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/05/02/openstack-newton-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 05:07:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/05/02/openstack-newton-install/</guid>
      <description>Newton is one the recent releases of OpenStack. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the Newton release of OpenStack on Ubuntu 16.04 as per the installation guide. As part of my blogging, book writing projects, I have the need to install OpenStack many times. And I have been automating the installation by writing simple shell scripts. The result is a collection of scripts that should help you get going with OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s latest release.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mitaka on Ubuntu – install scripts for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/07/06/mitaka-on-ubuntu-install-scripts-for-openstack/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 06:45:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/07/06/mitaka-on-ubuntu-install-scripts-for-openstack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mitaka is the most recent release of OpenStack and currently it is supports &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.openstack.org/mitaka/install-guide-ubuntu/&#34;&gt;Ubuntu 14.04 LTS (trusty)&lt;/a&gt;. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the Mitaka release of OpenStack on Ubuntu. As part of my blogging, book writing projects, I have had the need to install OpenStack many times. And I have been automating the installation by writing simple shell scripts. The result is a collection of scripts that should help you get going with OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s latest release.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wired and Wireless network on Ubuntu for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/06/29/wired-wireless-network-ubuntu-openstack/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2014 18:16:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/06/29/wired-wireless-network-ubuntu-openstack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In data center and cloud environment, servers used for hosting the virtual machines usually have more than one wired networking interfaces. In fact there are multiple Ethernet interfaces on each server. It is common practice to use one of the interface for &amp;lsquo;managing&amp;rsquo; the host itself. This interface is usually accessible from corporate networks and administrators will use this interface for doing SSH into the server. The other interfaces are usually used for virtual machine traffic or storage traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 Tools for Increasing Productivity</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/01/14/4-tools-for-more-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2013 13:30:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2013/01/14/4-tools-for-more-productivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, you are probably aware of the importance of productivity. In today&amp;#8217;s day and age a boost in productivity can help a long way in our personal and professional lives. Better productivity helps us adapt to expectations from a fast changing world. In this blog I share 4 tools that can help you improve your productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>