<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nova on Sriram S - Innervoice</title>
    <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/tags/nova/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nova on Sriram S - Innervoice</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 02:39:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/tags/nova/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Ocata release install scripts for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/06/03/ocata-openstack-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 02:39:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/06/03/ocata-openstack-install/</guid>
      <description>Ocata is the most recent release of OpenStack. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the Ocata is the most recent release of OpenStack. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the server as per the installation guide. This is a collection of scripts that should help you get going with OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s latest release. I have been developing these scripts to help me with my blogging and personal learning projects</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newton release install scripts for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/05/02/openstack-newton-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 05:07:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/05/02/openstack-newton-install/</guid>
      <description>Newton is one the recent releases of OpenStack. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the Newton release of OpenStack on Ubuntu 16.04 as per the installation guide. As part of my blogging, book writing projects, I have the need to install OpenStack many times. And I have been automating the installation by writing simple shell scripts. The result is a collection of scripts that should help you get going with OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s latest release.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Networking – an introduction</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2014 19:56:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I continue the series on virtual networking with an overview of OpenStack networking concepts. OpenStack is an open source project with an aim to create a scalable cloud operating platform. The primary goal of this software platform is to help build public and private clouds. Specifically it allows users to build and operate infrastructure as a service or &lt;strong&gt;IaaS&lt;/strong&gt; clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>