<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Sriram S - Innervoice</title>
    <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Sriram S - Innervoice</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 18:18:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals for the first half of 2018</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2018/01/07/goals-for-the-first-half-of-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 18:18:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2018/01/07/goals-for-the-first-half-of-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A very happy new year to the readers of my blogs. It is time for the semi-annual update about my blogging and learning goals. And I must say there are some interesting goals that I conjuring up for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker Compose with nginx and NodeJS</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/11/26/docker-compose-nginx-nodejs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 05:15:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/11/26/docker-compose-nginx-nodejs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are a follower of this blog, you might have read about &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2017/11/19/using-docker-nginx-nodejs/&#34;&gt;Using Docker with nginx and NodeJS&lt;/a&gt;. In this blog, I will discuss the code to build  the two containers using Docker Compose. Finally, I will highlight an important capability of Docker that I learnt in this exercise. The source code being referred in this blog is &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/sBmSt3&#34;&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Docker with nginx and NodeJS</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/11/19/using-docker-nginx-nodejs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 05:56:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/11/19/using-docker-nginx-nodejs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The best way to learn a new technology is by doing some hands-on practice or exercise. In order to learn the basics of Docker, I was scouting for a problem and the one that captured my imagination was how to use Docker for handling static web pages and dynamic REST APIs. In this 2-part blog, I will describe the problem and the solution first and then show how I implemented the solution using Docker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals for the second half of 2017</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/07/07/goals-2h-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 18:27:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/07/07/goals-2h-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The customary update about my blogging and learning goals is here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ocata release install scripts for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/06/03/ocata-openstack-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 02:39:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/06/03/ocata-openstack-install/</guid>
      <description>Ocata is the most recent release of OpenStack. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the Ocata is the most recent release of OpenStack. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the server as per the installation guide. This is a collection of scripts that should help you get going with OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s latest release. I have been developing these scripts to help me with my blogging and personal learning projects</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newton release install scripts for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/05/02/openstack-newton-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 05:07:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/05/02/openstack-newton-install/</guid>
      <description>Newton is one the recent releases of OpenStack. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the Newton release of OpenStack on Ubuntu 16.04 as per the installation guide. As part of my blogging, book writing projects, I have the need to install OpenStack many times. And I have been automating the installation by writing simple shell scripts. The result is a collection of scripts that should help you get going with OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s latest release.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals for the first half of 2017</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/02/02/goals-first-half-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 04:10:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/02/02/goals-first-half-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;First of all a very happy new year to all the readers. The fact that this blog comes more than a month into 2017 should give you hints on what sort of goals I have planned for 2017 first half. I will start with an assessment of the second half of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Horizon: extending the dashboard – Part 2</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/01/22/openstack-horizon-extending-dashboard-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 17:42:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2017/01/22/openstack-horizon-extending-dashboard-part-2/</guid>
      <description>In this second installment of my blog on OpenStack Horizon, I will take you through different source code files that make a custom OpenStack dashboard. As a recap from the first installment, I will show you how to create a custom dashboard to view all the Neutron &amp;ldquo;ports&amp;rdquo; in your OpenStack based cloud.
Enabling OpenStack Horizon Dashboard Django framework loads and enables dashboards based on entries present in the enabled directory of OpenStack Dashboard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Horizon: extending the dashboard – Part 1</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/12/27/openstack-horizon-customizing-the-dashboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 10:31:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/12/27/openstack-horizon-customizing-the-dashboard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OpenStack Horizon is the project that provides the web based dashboard for OpenStack based clouds. In this 2-part blog I will show you how you can extend the dashboard. Customizing and extending is one of the most powerful capabilities in OpenStack and in private cloud environments it is common to add additional enhancements to address an organization&amp;rsquo;s needs.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WILT – mysql, root and sudo</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/11/13/wilt-mysql-root-and-sudo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 16:44:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/11/13/wilt-mysql-root-and-sudo/</guid>
      <description>I came across an interesting behavior that helped me learn something about MySQL (MariaDB to be precise) authentication. In this WILT blog I will talk about the &amp;ldquo;unix socket&amp;rdquo; authentication plugin in MySQL/MariaDB. The steps shown in this blog have been tried on Ubuntu 16.04 and MariaDB Server 10.
MariaDB Install and root user In some earlier versions of MySQL as well as MariaDB server, the installation process required you to enter password for root user.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Announcement and Launch discounts</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/10/26/book-announcement-launch-discounts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 14:57:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/10/26/book-announcement-launch-discounts/</guid>
      <description>My second book titled &amp;ldquo;Software Defined Networking with OpenStack&amp;rdquo; is almost ready to be available publicly. You can find the overview of the book below.
With OpenStack Summit going on in Barcelona, my publishers, Packt, have graciously announced pre-launch discounts for the new book. You can get the following discounts:
 15% off on Print copies (code: SDNWOS15) 50% off on eBooks (code: SDNWOS50)  Both discounts available at my publisher website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals for second half of 2016</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/07/06/goals-for-second-half-of-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 07:19:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/07/06/goals-for-second-half-of-2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is that time of the year again - time to share my blogging and learning goals for the second half of 2016. Let’s start with a review of the first half of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mitaka on Ubuntu – install scripts for OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/07/06/mitaka-on-ubuntu-install-scripts-for-openstack/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 06:45:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/07/06/mitaka-on-ubuntu-install-scripts-for-openstack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mitaka is the most recent release of OpenStack and currently it is supports &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.openstack.org/mitaka/install-guide-ubuntu/&#34;&gt;Ubuntu 14.04 LTS (trusty)&lt;/a&gt;. I would like to share scripts that can be used to install the Mitaka release of OpenStack on Ubuntu. As part of my blogging, book writing projects, I have had the need to install OpenStack many times. And I have been automating the installation by writing simple shell scripts. The result is a collection of scripts that should help you get going with OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s latest release.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack Controller Logs – view using a browser</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/06/27/openstack-controller-logs-view-using-browser/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2016 18:22:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/06/27/openstack-controller-logs-view-using-browser/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OpenStack is made up of various services. These services have their own logs stored under /var/log directory. While working on OpenStack related projects it is quite common to monitor the logs for any problems or errors. While the tail command is the most popular, there are many benefits of using web browser to view the logs. In this blog let us see how we can view OpenStack Controller Logs using a browser.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals for the first half of 2016</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/02/01/goals-for-the-first-half-of-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 05:17:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/02/01/goals-for-the-first-half-of-2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am late by a month in sharing my blogging and learning goals for the first half of 2016. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with a review of the second half of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PyCharm and OpenStack programming</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/01/02/pycharm-and-openstack-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 17:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2016/01/02/pycharm-and-openstack-programming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OpenStack is based on the Python programming language and DevStack is the most common development and test environment for OpenStack. If you are doing serious, professional programming around OpenStack, it is very useful to have a proper development environment. In this blog, I will show you how to use the &lt;strong&gt;PyCharm IDE&lt;/strong&gt; from Jetbrains for your OpenStack programming. I will use the &lt;strong&gt;Neutron ML2 driver code from my book &lt;a href=&#34;http://goo.gl/TeXSYQ&#34;&gt;OpenStack Networking Cookbook&lt;/a&gt; to guide you&lt;/strong&gt; in setting up the PyCharm IDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ip vs. ifconfig – WILT</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/11/27/ip-vs-ifconfig-wilt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2015 06:54:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/11/27/ip-vs-ifconfig-wilt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular networking command in Linux is the ifconfig command. It lets you see (and configure) IP address for network interface. It also shows the MAC address for each interface. The MAC address and the IP address viewing is probably the most common reason for using the ifconfig command. In addition the ifconfig command works with physical network interface (like eth0..) and virtual network interface (like &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2013/12/08/tap-interfaces-linux-bridge/&#34;&gt;Tap interface&lt;/a&gt; etc).
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing: OpenStack Networking Cookbook</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/10/23/openstack-networking-cookbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2015 16:47:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/10/23/openstack-networking-cookbook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My first publication &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/1NrKjty&#34;&gt;OpenStack Networking Cookbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is now available for purchase. It is available as a printed book as well as e-book. OpenStack is a rapidly evolving cloud platform and Networking (Neutron) is one of its critical components. The current trends of SDN and NFV make OpenStack Networking even more exciting and complex. I have co-authored the book with a colleague and the overall experience of writing a book was very satisfying.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My goals for the second half of 2015</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/07/05/my-goals-for-the-second-half-of-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 17:30:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/07/05/my-goals-for-the-second-half-of-2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I have been doing for last few years, it is time to assess how well I have done on my blogging and learning goals. I will also share my goals for the second half of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ports in OpenStack Neutron</title>
      <link>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/07/04/ports-in-openstack-neutron/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2015 18:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/2015/07/04/ports-in-openstack-neutron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OpenStack supports rich abstractions to handle &lt;a href=&#34;http://reachsrirams.github.io/blogs/blogs/2014/04/06/openstack-networking/&#34;&gt;virtual networking needs in a cloud&lt;/a&gt;. As a user the most visible entities are the Network, Subnets, Routers, Firewall etc. But if we consider ingress and egress points for data traffic, the most critical entity is the Port. OpenStack Neutron Ports are usually created automatically as part of other user operations. However the CLI allows users to create Ports independently as well.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>